Finding Aid for Lawrence N. Steinberg Papers, 1936-1969 and 1996
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Lawrence N. Steinberg papers 1936-1969, 1996
Steinberg, Lawrence N., 1905-
19 oversize volumes
1.5 linear feet
05136 Aa 2
Career labor organizer; president of Ohio local of the Teamster Union, later appointed personal representative of the general president of the Union, Dave Beck and James Hoffa. The collection includes photographs, scrapbooks, and personal materials.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Richard L. Steinberg (donor no. 9521 ) and came to the library in September 2005.
Collection is open for research.
Lawrence Steinberg was a career labor organizer beginning in the mid-1930s as secretary-manager of Local 104 of the Retail Paint, Hardware, and Auto Accessories Employees Union of the United Retail and Wholesale Employees of America-CIO. He resigned in 1940 as a paid employee but continued on as president. Later that same year, he became organizational director for Local 1250 of the New York Department Store Employees' Union. In 1942, his activities on behalf of the Retail, Wholesale and Department Stores Union earned him the assignment of Ohio State Director, headquartered in Toledo. In 1948, he severed his relationship with the union, while guiding the retail workers to affiliate with the Teamsters, becoming Local 22. In May 1953, the delegates to Joint Council No. 44 elected Steinberg as their President In 1955, Local 22 merged into Local 20 with Steinberg as president, a position he held until 1969. In 1956, he was appointed to the position of Personal Representative to the General President of the Teamsters Union, first Dave Beck, then James Hoffa. Steinberg retired from the union activities in 1969.
The Steinberg collection documents the career of this union organizer. The materials have been arranged into two series: Biographical/Miscellaneous and Scrapbooks.
Subjects:
Steinberg, Lawrence N., 1905-; Clerks (Retail trade)--Labor unions.; Beck, Dave, 1894-1993; Hoffa, James R. (James Riddle), 1913-; International Brotherhood of Teamsters, Chauffeurs, Warehousemen, and Helpers of America.; Labor leaders--United States.; Labor unions--United States--Officials and employees.; Strikes and lockouts--New York (State)--New York.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Steinberg, Lawrence N., 1905-; Beck, Dave, 1894-1993; Hoffa, James R. (James Riddle), 1913-; International Brotherhood of Teamsters, Chauffeurs, Warehousemen, and Helpers of America.; Labor leaders--United States.; Labor unions--Ohio.; Retail trade strikes--New York (State)--New York.; Strikes--New York (State)--New York.; Pickets--New York (State)--New York.; Women--Meetings--New York (State)--New York.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Scrapbooks.
- Biographical/Miscellaneous
  The Biographical/Miscellaneous series is noteworthy for photographs of Steinberg's work in the 1940s with a strike of retail workers in New York. The images are of women workers voting to go out on strike. There are also images of Teamster presidents Dave Beck and James Hoffa at various union functions.
  - Program containing biographical sketch entitled, " Just Say He was a Union Man" -- Larry Steinberg, September 2, 1996 (Box 1)
  - Loose photographs, with groupings that include Dave Beck, James R. Hoffa, and other Teamsters officials (Box 1)
    (the photographs were used in the biographical sketch of LS with full identification)
  - Photographs album with images from the dedication of the Teamsters headquarters in Toledo, Ohio, circa 1958 (Box 1)
    (include group photos that include Dave Beck and James Hoffa)
  - Album of correspondence received in recognition of his receiving an Honorary Doctorate of Law from the University of Toledo December 1966-January 1967 (Box 1)
  - Court transcript (partial) of US v. James R. Hoffa 1962 (Box 1)
  - Publications: Minneapolis "Sedition" trial (Box 1)
  - Photographs album/scrapbook, 1936-1942 (Box 2)
    (include clippings, photographs, and other documentation)
- Scrapbooks
  The Scrapbook series covers the period of 1944-1945 and 1956 to 1969 and consists of clippings (mainly Toledo, OH) from general distribution and union newspapers detailing Teamster activities.
  - December 1944-January 1945 Montgomery Ward strike (Volume 19)
  - May 23, 1956-August 30, 1956 (Volume 1)
  - November 1, 1956-May 1957 (Volume 2)
  - May 28, 1957-September 26, 1957 (Volume 3)
  - February 28, 1957-October 26, 1957 (Volume 4)
  - January 6, 1958-January 7, 1959 (Volume 5)
  - June 25, 1959-May 5, 1960 (Volume 6)
  - May 7, 1960-October 14, 1961 (Volume 7)
  - September 17, 1962-April 8, 1963 (Volume 8)
  - March 9, 1964-July 31, 1964 (Volume 9)
  - August 1, 1964-December 19, 1964 (Volume 10)
  - 1965 (Volume 11)
  - January-June 1966 (Volume 12)
  - July December 1966 (Volume 13)
  - August-December 1967 (Volume 14)
  - January-November 1968 (Volume 15)
  - December 1968 (Volume 16)
  - January-June 1969 (Volume 17)
  - July-December 1969 (Volume 18)